hello everyone and welcome back to
active inference insights I'm your host
darus P way and today I have the
pleasure to chat to Alexander orobia
Professor orobia is an assistant
professor of computer science at
Rochester Institute of Technology where
he directs the neural adaptive Computing
laboratory his work focuses on
developing new learning procedures and
computational architectures that embody
various properties biological
neurocircuitry and are Guided by
theories of mind and brain functionality
last year he published the paper mortal
computation a foundation for biometic
intelligence with Carl friston which
grounded the Mortal computation thesis
in the active inference framework in
which they argued that active inference
might prove useful in guiding the
construction of computational systems
Alex thank you so much for joining me
it's been a little while since we've
done one of these so I'm going to be a
little bit Rusty um as exemplified by my
my pronunciation of the word labor Tre
uh lab I normally just go for lab um how
are you I'm doing great thank you for
having me on and uh no you're very
welcome you can call it laboratory it
sounds nice and formal I like it yeah
laboratory lab um great well before we
dive into that paper I wanted to ask
you're kind of coming from a
computational
background um I've never actually asked
this question first up to a guest but it
struck me that I probably should which
is how did you come across active
inference as a as a framework oh that's
that that's a nice question
um well it was a few years ago and the
short compressed version of that is that
I was working with some uh colleagues in
the Imaging science department here at
RIT they do eye tracking and uh
cognitive science research I also have a
cognitive Science Background or part
partial background in my Gra grad school
years and uh so as we were uh talking
about building computational models for
uh ey tracking problems uh we we ended
up settling on this reinforcement
learning Dynamic control formulation of
the particular problem we were solving
and uh I had been long thinking about
biological process models for
reinforcement learning control and so I
was already aware for a very long time
of the free energy principes so I
because I I'm a predictive coding
researcher I like to also pitch that as
something I have quite a body of work uh
build been building a body of work on
and so active inference is like an
extension of that right it's basically
say let me put action into this process
and actively sample the environment uh
to facilitate my self- evidencing and so
uh it just kind of made sense that we
would maybe look at the free energy
principle originally wanted to build
predictive coding models of our
reinforcement learning system and then
we said well wait a minute uh
exploration is going to be a difficult
component here and that's what active
inference brings one of the big things
it brings to the table uh to use Carl's
phrase uh which is this epistemic
foraging I the idea that we're doing
intelligent exploration driven by our
surprisal and so it just kind of made
sense to investigate this framework in a
in a in a further further away uh and
then since then it what was nice about
that group is that uh my my colleagues
uh weren't very familiar with uh
predictive coding so I gave them a talk
and then we wanted to understand active
inference so we had a little reading
group that we established with the grad
students the other faculty and uh you
know we had forced ourselves to dive a
bit deeper into for example Carl's work
um Chris Buckley's work as well so I was
already familiar with Chris even before
I actually got to meet him
years later um and then one of our one
of my primary grad students uh George he
was uh actually building some active
inference models uh and then we
effectively settled on a version of that
in our it tracking problem and actually
that led to a really nice article about
last year with George in h frontiers of
computational Neuroscience where we
actually published a little model uh
that did very simple active inference uh
in a in a in a a gaze modeling task and
a very simple tracking task so it was
really nice and uh yeah and as then I
guess to wrap up that story without uh
waxing too much about my past um uh
because of that uh and my fascination
with predictive coding circuitry and
biologic biological modeling um I sort
of branched off in parallel to while
George was working on that project to
say um why isn't active inference even
though Carl has presented it in several
ways
uh uh in terms of predictive coding why
aren't we building things in this very
very raw low-level model right because
the idea is a lot of active interest use
back propagation of Errors deep neural
networks great idea gets you to scale it
up um but uh I have a long history of uh
being at odds with back propagation and
uh and the non-biological ways we do
deep learning and so I had a series of
papers over the last few years where uh
I was saying uh let's to active
inference uh completely Wholesale in
terms of predictive coding and so that
that eventually accumulated in a a
robotic control paper I believe that got
published beginning of last year too uh
and that was really nice because that's
like completely done in terms of
predictive coding um so that's I think
I'll stop there that's sort of how I
found my way uh into the deep active
inference corollary of the free energy
principle which I've already danced over
the years by saying that uh the models
that I build are doing like a an
approximate version of very oral free
energy minimization so right right yeah
yeah you bought there's a lot there um I
think it's interesting yeah in in the
best way possible there's a lot there in
so far
as I guess free the fre free energy
principle and active inference is kind
of hierarchical in of itself as a
theoretical framework because yes we're
minimizing our variational free energy
but the way that we're doing that is
kind of still up for grabs whether it's
predicted processing in continuous State
spaces whether it's a kind of more um
message passing scheme like a pom DP
scheme I think people don't realize that
those debates or those theoretical
Frameworks are still getting fleshed out
um so it's it it makes sense why you
know it is totally viable to push in One
Direction maybe against back propagation
and pro predictive coding for example um
you also brought up reinforcement
learning we I'd like to backtrack to
that later on in the conversation
because I'm sure you know you all know
far more than I do there's kind of this
live debate again still whether
reinforcement learning is going to get
us there um and we can talk about the
developments uh in that domain but as I
mentioned in my introduction really what
I want to speak about is this paper uh
mortal computation a foundation for
biometic
intelligence which I got to say I really
really loved reason why I wanted to have
you on is because I really really
enjoyed that paper I'm coming at this
from a sort of cognitive science
philosophy background and I thought it
was really impressive the way that you
managed to integrates loads of different
Frameworks from sort of pure machine
learning and physics to philosophy
phenomenology and cognitive science so
there's going to be loads for us to talk
about before we sort of dive into the
details I'm sure plenty of people have
heard the uh out of the how many words
are there in the title seven they might
be a bit confused about a couple of them
so two questions feel free to take them
in whatever order you wish the first is
what do you mean by mortal computation
and what is biomimetic
intelligence okay um yeah that's a good
way to start these terms might not be
thrown around enough in enough Fields um
so biomimetic intelligence you some
might have heard of biomimicry right
which is the idea we're copying uh that
is that which is biotic or biological or
natural uh and the idea is that we look
to Natural organism
maybe animals humans even very very
simple life forms as you know you
brought up in the paper um there's we
use a lot of different examples to
exemplify Concepts and the idea of
biomimetic intelligence is we say well
for example an animal is intelligent is
able to engage in certain Behavior it is
able to adapt to certain aspects of its
environment it's able to forage it's
able to uh do a whole variety of
cognitive tasks and um the idea of
biometic intelligence is that in the
Sciences of the artificial with an art
AR uh what do you call it a
technological artifact uh something that
isn't maybe naturally we would argue
biotic it is in silico uh or uh you know
non-biological material can we get this
object to emulate or simulate various
properties and aspects of that biotic
organisms uh Behavior so that is where
the biomimicry comes we are sort of
copying that which we have observed in
nature something that is natural and
trying to instill this in some
mechanical computational fashion in uh a
technological artifact that is not
grounded in that natural biotic kind of
setting so that's broadly what you could
say is biomic intelligence and of course
you could also take that another step
further and think of artificial
intelligence right in its own very word
artificial means we are really building
something that is essentially divorced
from what we would call Natural or
biological this is in the you know in
silico systems that we have today uh
biomedic intelligence says well maybe we
should move a little towards what we
would call naturalistic artificial
intelligence something that draws its
inspiration at the very least if not
maybe Faithfully modeling because
there's also different degrees of how
close you get to biology in nature uh
and can we construct artificial systems
that are intelligent and adaptive uh
that maybe for example emulate what a a
cat would do when it's you know in its
natural environment and uh trying to for
example hunt for mice or hunt for food
um and then just as a quick fun word to
tag on that because we also use that in
the paper bionic engineering is actually
the application
of biomic intelligence or the uh the
idea of actually formulating this and
solving a real world task or problem and
that can also start to bleed and it's
kind of interesting part of the other
fun of writing this paper is learning a
little bit of the history and the
origins of words and uh who defines this
and everyone has kind of a different
definition of these but uh bionic
intelligence could kind of bleed into
hybrid systems like oh human augmented
systems maybe we're you know creating
cyborgs or uh you know enhancing uh a
natural organism in some way that they
don't have with their own actual body or
form so bionic intelligence is kind of
bionic engineering is a little bit
broader but I just like to tag that on
because we also kind of abbreviate them
sometimes we'll Carl and I will say
biomimetics but that's just biomimetic
intelligence um uh at least the way we
refer to it and then bionics is bionic
engineering so I think that'll stop
there because we could keep going on
there's a lot of history behind biomic
intelligence and bionic engineering so
mortal computation which is kind of at
the heart and core of this
paper I mean obviously it takes the
entire paper to sort of scope it out I I
will first pay homage and respect to my
uh my friend Jeff Jeff Hinton he's
actually the one that introduced that
very phrase uh beginning of December of
last year if I recall correctly um in
one of of his papers so again I work a
lot in biological credit assignment how
do we train neural systems in a
biologically inspired fashion and so
Jeff had a paper on the Ford Ford
algorithm and so I was in correspondence
with him about that not too long after
that came out and worked on some things
of my own but he introduced in that
paper in about a paragraph or two uh
just talking about Mortal computation as
just this kind of concept of uh hardware
and the relationship to software and how
those two uh you know we treat them in
computer science specifically and I'm
going to fold hopefully no one that
might watch this might uh you know uh
get angry at this but I also fold
computer science with cybernetics uh
because you know there's all the
computational components and uh there's
a lot of entanglement if you look at
their history too so the ideas that we
treat in many sense software as Immortal
that means it can be run on any platform
it doesn't really matter uh the hardware
or substrate that it is instantiated on
uh and again we can I we tie it in this
paper to machine learning and deep
learning uh which is just effectively a
program that is data driven and tries to
adapt based on uh input that we give to
the system and uh those are no different
they're like any other computer program
they you could take for example chat GPT
or any of the big transformers of today
and if your uh you know your GPU server
falls apart uh you can just take that
program that you've saved on dis
elsewhere and run it on another one and
it will behave roughly the same um and
so that's what makes it Immortal uh you
can copy this anywhere you want mortal
computation says well we we should
consider the fact and again this is just
a little bit based on and we we flesh
this out a little bit more than I think
Jeff at least wanted to at the time
which is that moral computation bounds
or entangles the software with the
hardware we we shouldn't be thinking of
them as two separate and distinct
entities um and so that's where the
phrase sort of originates and one of the
core motivations uh is that um we get a
certain Energy Efficiency um because one
of the biggest criticisms of uh
Transformers and neural models today
that characterize artificial
intelligence is that they are they
greatly energy inefficient uh they they
require a lot of compute uh and while
the costs are going down and I'm seeing
some of those Trends pop up uh they they
leave a pretty big carbon footprint um
and so that's there's also a fun and
another vein of research that got into
this paper of my own is I've been
studying green AI versus red AI uh and
you know just like we talk about green
initiatives because we you know care
about uh global climate change and our
concerns of what's Happening to our
planet and our environment um that's
green AI we would want to build
intelligence systems that don't leave
such a big carbon footprint uh red AI is
what we currently have and there was
some really nice studies Emma strubel
many many years ago put out one of the
first uh measurements of these language
large language models um and so mortal
computation uh is one way to address
this great inefficiency um Beyond a lot
of other things but that's kind of where
at least Jeff uh was coming at this from
um what kind of funny just as a quick
side note uh because I obviously track
Jeff's work and uh well he in December
you know sort of went down the route of
you know we should you know get rid of
back propop we should go to some
biological form of learning and here's
my really wonderful idea uh and Mortal
computation sort of one of those goals
uh later he sort of I noticed used that
as an interesting counterargument to
talk about
the dangers of immortal computation as
he's talking today about you know the
potential threats uh that Immortal
systems like chat GPT and Transformers
like them and other models not just
these large language models posed to
humanity and it's bringing up an
interesting discussion and thoughts
about you know an ex existential crisis
for Humanity and worthy things to be
talking about but he sort of steered in
the direction I noticed he uses moral
computation sort of as like a well
that's what you know we would say maybe
the brain and you know biological
organisms do uh but the models that we
have today don't do that and actually
that gives them sort of like superpowers
and some dangerous abilities that we
can't do with humans and that's worthy
of discussion but we obviously don't go
into that in this paper um so that's
where it sort of originated and then
just to sort of quickly cap it off
because I know you said you want to talk
more about the paper because the whole
paper goes into What would mean to be
mortal computation uh I also really
liked in one of the talks that my friend
Carl gave or had with someone else I was
interviewing him about this work too and
he said that uh this paper's form of
mortal computation is sort of like
another take on the concept so again
like what I explained was sort of what
Jeff meant by it um and then that was
his launching point for a set of other
arguments um this one says well wait a
minute that entanglement can we
characterize that and dig into that a
lot deeper and so the idea is that that
gets us to the origins of life right of
how we ourselves you and me Darius are
mortal computers in effect right right
if we don't mind calling ourselves that
and you know not trying to remove our
humanity and so that's what sort of this
survey paper ends up becoming is it says
well okay if we wanted to really go down
that rabbit hole if you will what does
it mean to Define a moral computer and
do other domains of science have
possible definitions and it that's what
the other fun thing about this paper I
know you didn't ask about its
motivations but what's nice about it is
that it is an echo of a lot of already
great ideas by people way smarter than
myself uh over the last century uh
talking about essentially what you could
call Immortal computation ranging from
biophysics and biology to physiology uh
to even cognitive science has already
some wonderful theoretical Frameworks
that we sort of just sharpened or
highlighted or there's a little section
in there where Carl and I extend one of
the cogni theories maybe we'll talk
about that later I like that you know
the we have it called the 5e cognitive
theory yes yeah yeah yeah cool yeah
that's fantastic um okay perfect so
there's yeah again Lots I want to unpick
there so before we fold in into inactive
inference more technically and talk
about how that is a framework uh in
which we can ground mortal
computation I want to ask a question
about the motivations about this Energy
Efficiency um because people might be
listening and saying well Immortal
computation sounds kind of nice um it's
kind of there and I can take it and it's
substrate independent and so um my
commitments are
fewer why why does it make more sense to
turn to a different form of computation
rather than just
refining um something which clearly
works and uh may be uh in the long run
it seems to me at least more efficient
in the sense that it's just more
transferable across different
domains um yeah that that in that we we
mentioned that a little bit in the
beginning of our paper why would we want
to commit ourselves to Mortal
computation it's rather brittle as you
pointed out so
um so again there's many different
reasons for why we would want a mortal
computer but you said the Energy
Efficiency so to let's just pick at that
little bit of the argument so near the
start of the paper we we talk about the
thermodynamic motivations for uh mortal
computers and there's some really nice
ideas from physics and information
Theory I mean there's uh even probably
more that we don't properly scope uh and
two of them that we can just briefly
mention are the land hour limit and jar
zinski inequality um when you in a
nutshell without getting technical about
them because we do I actually made a
point to flesh out those equations just
so readers would be like if they're not
familiar they can look at them but
really at the end of the day those two
concepts say there is a uh a bound on
the amount of work or the thermodynamic
thermodynamic cost that A system can
have to write and store information so
again in a computer um you know the idea
is that we're using bits to you know
store things in memory um and so
basically what those two say is that uh
there's a point where we're not going to
get any more thermodynamic efficiently
about you know the cost of actually
racing a bit I believe that's what the
landar limit or sorry yeah the landar
limit and J inquality partially touch on
they also talk about random fluctuations
and averaging things to get a system to
an equilibrium state um but at the end
of the day it's all just about that
there's going to be a a lower bound that
we can't breach any further and what
does that actually imply for computer
science actually computer scientists
have written about uh these physical
limits uh and the thermodynamic costs
and it says that it might mean that we
want to reach something called inmemory
computation so inmemory Computing
basically just says that we want to
conduct the mathematical computational
calculations let's
those that characterize neuronal
simulations directly at the chip right
so the idea is that we have processing
and we have it organized let's say in a
crossbar in a neuromorphic chip and we
use that as like one of our little
examples and we can actually essentially
construct the neural model in that
memory crossbar and so like the neurons
are arranged in a particular way
physically actually in this little chip
and the synapses relate you know are
related to for example memory ERS right
and the ideas that we transmit
information across these and that will
be at the lower limit or the the bound
on computation why is this different
than what we do today well today uh
Transformers and the like regardless of
the value of gpus and how and even what
what are they call tpus tensor
processing units uh and the the speed
that they have afforded us and that's
actually partially one of the core
reasons of the de the what do you call
catalysts of the deep learning
Revolution uh is that we use Von noyman
architecture so the idea in that is that
there's a greater cost Associated just
fundamentally by simulating these neural
models on a vanon noyman architecture
and that's because you could look at for
example the memory organization of a
computer so uh Beyond you know like
let's just call it slow longterm memory
systems which you know you can write and
this will preserve your information when
you turn off your computer and turn it
on later we kind of want that uh versus
volatile memory which is something that
is really fast doesn't give you much of
a cost to store things but it's volatile
so obviously if you turn things off that
you can't be guaranteed that your
information is stored on there and then
there's different types of intermediate
memory and so the way of annoyment
architecture sort of is structured is it
arranges this memory in a hierarchical
fashion and the CPU lives or the GPU if
you will but let's just say the CPU
specifically lives on top of this memory
hierarchy that's where your computer
programming lives that's where our
neural network is being executed by the
the compiler which talks to the
assembler and it talks to the bits at
the very low level of the computer and
so that's where your mathematical model
is but it needs data it needs
information it needs the matrices or
tensors that store the synaptic weights
right let's just think of our
traditional neural network it's just a
bunch of Matrix multiplications and some
nonlinearities well you need to retrieve
that me that weight Matrix for the first
layer well that lives at the very very
bottom of this hierarchy so there needs
to be some transfer process and that's
already exhibiting a great thermod
denamic cost they've Quantified that I
remember putting in the paper like
certain uh measurements of jewels at
different layers so already
fundamentally we are not operating as
close to the lower limit on
thermodynamic cost as we could be um and
so that's already right there you that
explains a great deal of the
thermodynamic
inefficiency of deep neural networks and
intelligence systems that we have today
um one of the motivations you can use
the idea of me inmemory comput uh
inmemory compute uh is that it gets you
to something like Edge Computing so if
you have something in robotics which I'm
very fascinated by robotic systems or
even autonomous vehicles um you're not
going to be able to transmit to servers
very easily right you're not going to be
offloading your intelligence somewhere
else uh because then you have the
communication cost to pay of
transmitting information you're going to
want your system to live in the device
that you're using so in a robotic system
you have limited power you have limited
uh compute resources so you're going to
want to work with in-memory Computing
like for example a great uh in-memory
system would be like a neuromorphic chip
just in case the audience is like well
what would be examples of that um and
one that has fascinated me which is
where the realm of spiking neuronet
comes into play and I have done research
in that as well and that's what gets you
to neuromorphic chips which does rest on
this principle of inmemory computing
right so the the actual spiking neuronal
models are actually laid out in these
neuromorphic chips and computation
happens directly on there so um I think
that's sort of like the uh the in energy
kind of argument for why we would want
this this would be quite useful for Edge
Computing cases and you you'd say well
okay well that's just a few examples
right right we're doing a lot of
intelligence without that but most of
Robotics is going to be Edge Computing
if we want an intelligent uh humanoid or
non-humanoid like robotic system um
we're not going to be running them on
big supercomputers or gpus and again I'm
not trying here to attack those that
maybe are for like hive mind
intelligence where we do communication
across servers and we can pay that cost
um but if we want these organic like
robotic systems this is where I think
mortal computation really uh is a path
forward for those types of applications
and there's a lot of other applications
that you could argue have Edge Computing
so um I think I'll stop there because
that just centers only on the
thermodynamic argument um I'll just
quickly before I forget it tag on uh the
other part of is that when we get to
that lower limit on thermodynamic cost
uh there's a nice equivalence to the
variational free energy minimization
process because uh while again I I did
tend to focus a little bit more on the
thermodynamics the physics side of
things you know I liked how Carl and I
sort of connected it to the information
theoretic idea that uh to be Baye
optimal right we want to actually get
close to that limit and so there's it's
sort of like there it's saying the same
thing actually the nice thing about the
variational free energy princip sorry
variational free energy minimization
process is it is also actually
optimizing that thermodynamic cost in
organic systems so we are operating at
that lower limit that's what it means to
be Bay's optimal free energy perspective
and I'll stop there but I like that I
just want to make that connection
because that kind of tags a little bit
in that argument and then it starts to
bleed into the other motivations you
could say for moral computation yeah
yeah yeah no I let's actually stick on
that because I think that's a really
interesting point um I think people some
you know it's it's actually possible to
kind of do the free energy principle
without taking into account
thermodynamics right you can just do the
statistical mechanics and the
information Theory just do Shannon
information and just say you know we're
reducing self information so people
might be curious actually how this ties
to thermodynamics I'm curious about how
ties to thermodynamics I'm not a
physicist
so to minimize variation on free energy
is to be sort of operating at this um
lower Bound in in terms of thermodynamic
energy what does that look like and I
think you talk in your paper about kind
of exchanging
um energy or or or the work needed to
maintain yourself at this bound
um what what what does that look like in
terms of the mapping between information
theoretic terms and
thermodynamic um
terms well first of all I'm not a
physicist either so we we should be
clear here as well I am a computer
scientist and cognitive scientist um so
again it goes back to like what I and I
mean I have my paper here just to remind
myself if I need to but like I said it
goes to the jarin INE equality and the
lar limit um so I guess maybe I want to
ask a little bit of a clarification what
do you mean what does it look like just
to help me out here to trigger that I'm
not so just in terms of that kind of
isomorphism um that minimizing
variational free energy just is
operating at this thermodynamic lower
bound MH just in very it can be very
simple because it's going to have to be
very simple for me um because they don't
teach you this stuff in cognitive
science enough yeah
um what does I mean what does that mean
um in terms of our sort of thermodynamic
exchanges with the environment
because you know I think a stumbling
block for a lot of people when they hear
about free energy is they there are lots
of ways of talking about energy so it's
kind of being able to do the mapping
between all the different aspects
whether we're talking about kind of
Shannon information or whether we're
talking about thermodynamic energy um or
we're talking about whatever whatever
you know whatever framework you want to
come uh you want to work with so just in
very simple
terms what does the minimization of I
mean can put put it very generally what
does the minimization of variational
free energy Bey Beyond moral computation
Beyond computers very simply what does
the minimization minimization of
variational en look like in terms of
operating at this thermodynamic lower
bound well I guess it gets a little
confusing because now I'm thinking about
the actual implementation so again I
could approach it from a predictive
coding point of view because that's what
I usually appeal to when I think of
minimizing variational free energy so I
guess at the end of the
day it kind of goes into I guess the
problem with your question I think it
makes me think of the other arguments we
get into metabolic efficiency and the
idea of resources that the organism is
acquiring uh okay um I think I know
where I want to go with this so uh it's
actually kind of later in the paper
where we touch back on the free energy
principle and we get into this concept
so what does this look like it looks
like the concept of the what do you call
it the non-equilibrium steady state the
Ness so what does this mean more
generally for even artificial and
biological organisms the idea is that we
want to reach a point that we are far
from thermodynamic equilibrium and so
yeah I gotta charge my memory here a
little bit of certain parts of the paper
so apologize for the delay there um so
the second law of Thermodynamics is that
you know that entropy must increase
right in in a closed system and so we
are tending towards higher entropy and
we are reaching you know systems will
reach equilibrium and actually that's
not what living systems are doing living
systems live at what I just said earlier
non-equilibrium and you'd say well wait
a minute are we trying to adhere to the
second law of Thermodynamics and this is
part of what was interesting about this
paper in in understanding the history of
things there is an interpretation of
thermodynamics and biology and they call
it the first law of thermody First Law
of biological thermodynamics at least
this is what I had found in my uh you
know
uh through the in through the literature
and the idea is that organisms do want
to stand far away from equilibrium
because equilibrium means death
equilibrium means dissolution or
disintegration into a heat bath into
your environment uh your identity ceases
to exist and that allows me to poke and
touch another concept of why mortal
computation is so important it's a
process of identity Constitution and
preservation and so uh where that
connection comes into into play is that
organisms they have a goal and according
to the free energy principle organisms
have this this the idea that their
Dynamics wants to make them stand away
from this non equil sorry from this
equilibrium and so they're going to need
energy and resources to allow themselves
to do that and then there's another part
to that and actually I do want to remind
myself so I don't steer the audience
wrong because I liked how I pitched it
or how I put it in the paper because
there are two principles that before you
got into the markof blanket discussion
oh no h okay I remember what yeah so
again it does connect to the markup
blanket but the idea is that these
Dynamics in the S the internal states of
the organism are conditionally
independent of their environment the
external States right and that's what
the markup blanket formalism tries to
formalize that more strongly and the
that we have those density Dynamics they
are conditionally independent however
you are still uh weakly coupled to the
environment through the maral blanket
interface and so again I'm apologize for
introducing those words later in case
you wanted me to flesh those out but uh
the idea is that because we are coupled
to our environment that also gets us to
the connections of active inference and
why we must act to move about our
environment so as to prevent to keep
ourselves at the non-equilibrium steady
state and the free energy principle says
that uh if you are a living organism or
an entity you will return to this NZ and
your action in your uh your goals and
behavior lead you back to the NES the
other concept is and this is the part
two of the free energy principle is the
concept of continual
self-evaluative model which is connects
to the other component of the paper
where we brought in cybernetics and like
the good regulator theorem which we
could talk about that later if you want
um so I think that's what it looks like
right it manifests itself in this this
continuous goal of trying to stay in
non-equilibrium you're avoiding
equilibrium which is dissolution into
your environment death which also means
the end of your identity um and so
that's what a mortal computer is
constantly engage in and that's what the
thermodynamics kind of gets you to it
walks you to that which is another way
that the free energy principle states
that right and so you can look at it
from the like the information theoretic
quantity of like oh I'm you know dealing
with gnats or bits right but the idea is
that the end of the day you trying to
stay in your nest
n steady state and you're continuously
self-evidence say uh and you're dealing
with this weekly coupled weak coupling
to your environment and you're
interacting through your markup blanket
I'll leave that black box for now in
case you want to poke at no that that
that's great I mean that that's much
more my language
ense my that's what I think it looks
like that's where the thermodynamics
really gets you into the biological
thermodynamics the first law biological
which is really what that is sort of
restating REM manipulating it's
basically all talking about that
non-equilibrium that we want to live at
which then you can and the nice thing
about the biological first law of
thermodynamics is it sort of deals with
the fact that you're saying well we
don't violate the second law of
Thermodynamics entropy will still go up
it's just not in the organism system
itself it's open system that lives in a
close system which is a greater like in
econ Niche organism pairing right and so
entropy will go up according to the
second law in the entire system but
inside this system this explains why
entropy can go down and that's what you
know and that's what I liked about that
because that was a great source of
confusion I saw even in the literature
um you know how are we dealing with the
actual second law of Thermodynamics well
we're not Viola we are really adhering
to the biological first law of
thermodynamics which that's what NES and
the free energy principle sort of at
least one dimension or the dimensions
that I'm more familiar with
tackle yeah so that great so that latter
point is kind of where I was heading
with my rubbish physics vocabulary but
the the nest and the TR to set stuff is
is is all perfect for us so don't worry
you haven't opened Pandora's Box because
this is a language at least that I'm
speaking these days and and this
institute is speaking but that's the
point I was making um because it's it's
kind of all about the the scope of one's
analysis right like equilibrium for whom
um because I think people get confused
that they they think of free energy uh
minimization as homeostasis which they
learned at school as equilibrium but
then they're saying that we're far from
equilibrium um so it's it's it's
non-equilibrium with respect to the
universe or with respect to the way the
universe wants to be which is
dissipative fundamentally right but it's
it's equilibrium for ourselves in terms
of our internal Dynamics given our
steady state you know given our
attractor set and I should add a word
that just complements what you said
because you're correct homeostasis is
actually kind of confusing and we
introduced another word uh and I thinkk
Carl for pointing me in this direction
because he he had us you know highlight
this hormesis I think
yes because it handles this and we could
talk about that if we want but I that's
the word people learn but I never
learned that when I was much younger I I
only learned that in the context of
formulating this framework with Carl so
yeah and then people uh I guess there's
a great deal of emphasis on allostasis
as well within active inflence which we
can touch on we we should probably
unpick those three yeah all thees and
don't forget autop poesis as well autop
poesis I've been reading a lot about
autop poesis um great okay
cool yeah I I mean should I keep
perusing down this area I think it's
interesting because it's like so we're
minimizing entropy within our
own bound within our own system whatever
that looks like because those boundaries
it's it's hard to kind of cast a
limit but that according to the second
law of D thermodynamics means that we
have to be creating entropy elsewhere
just so that the system itself is
abiding by the second
law um
what how do we do that how does anything
do that where where are we creating
entropy creating ah okay
well let me make sure that I zoom in on
the right component that touches on that
so I think the problem is there's all
these slices to Mortal computation as
you're familiar with the paper and I
think a piece of one of the other
interpretations is a more approachable
way to understand how we increase
entropy which is the idea of in activism
so this is I'm I'm borrowing from so
just for the audience that maybe hasn't
read the paper uh we intro we we sort of
have a pathway that we talk about the
Mortal computation thesis we talk about
biophysics we talk about the cybernetics
interpretation we talk about the
cognitive science uh framing right even
though they don't use these words
they're essentially saying these ideas
and then we lead into sort of a free
energy definition and a Markov blanket
formulation with uh other things and
then we lead to a definition so that's
so when I say slices that third of that
one portion of the paper on cognitive
science is where we borrow uh from uh
well what's normally called 4E cognitive
theory which you know and one of those e
is inactive the first one's embodiment
which we can touch on that one as well
but uh inactive is about your
relationship to your environment and so
uh and how that interacts with you
there's like a bidirectional
relationship we act on our environment
and that effectively means we are
authors of the
information uh that we will end up using
and uh the resources that come into us
right in terms of our foraging in terms
of our survival remember not to forget
our goal is to stay in non equilibrium
right the non equilibrium steady state
and so uh That's essential how we're
going to end up creating entropy right
because we are going to manipulate the
environment the idea where the active
portion the active inference element
comes into play nice and so we are uh
what's the right word that we use in the
in in the paper that others have used as
well uh we are engaged in Niche
construction right indeed yeah so
because we manipulate the environment
using the affordances that it brings us
and we do things to allow ourselves to
again you could Tye this for those that
maybe don't like Ness as the goal but
say we want to survive survival and
identity con continuance right is
essentially living in this
non-equilibrium steady state uh we enact
our environment we change it and then
that information of course we're then
Gathering that and so the environment
affects us right it's a bidirectional
relation the environment uh constrains
us puts uh problems on us we have to
deal with that but we change the
environment so we are creating disorder
and that's I think key element is that
through the actions that you take
through any animal that that they take
uh through any organism that they do to
manipulate and change something about
their environment so that way they could
continue to get resources uh matter and
energy uh those are the two the fuels of
the work Universe right uh we we
essentially create that disorder right
and so that's how the second law of
Thermodynamics get satisfied because
that's what biological or biotic
entities and I'll just zoom in on them
for now because you know again I want to
be careful not to step on physicist Toes
or biophysicist toes as well because I'm
not in those domains I've just read
enough of that work to synthesize right
um but that's how you're creating your
entropy is that you are inactive right
and so this is the concept of inactive
uh cognition you said you're reading
about autop poesis there's also this
thing called what is it uh autop poetic
inactiv M as well yeah Evan Thompson
yeah exactly yeah I I've just I'm
rereading mind and life which is Evan
Thompson's kind of massive magnum opus
from 2007 which is which is cracking um
I like pointing people in directions of
readings that they can do um so yeah
that's a great one Thompson's someone
everyone should read I think yeah yeah
so yeah beautiful stuff um obviously
verel rush and Thompson 91 the embody
mind and all the stuff that did with
matano 1980 Al pus all wonderful work
yeah in mind in life he talks about the
fact that
inactive uh entities are uh what does he
say he says operationally closed um but
sense making and by sense making I think
what he means is this kind of yeah
thermodynamically open um so we're in
the game of autop
paresis but that that doesn't deny that
doesn't negate the possibility of
obviously of interacting with the
environment in fact we have to integrate
the environment into our model or into
our uh action policies to use an active
inference term in order to Eng like do
autop pesis you're not going to last
very long if you're an entirely closed
off system um it's funny because again
it just makes me think about how scale
how scale is really a very important
kind of currency in this discussion and
it might just be philosophically
interesting but I'm sure it's
interesting for physicist to too mhm
because it makes me think that like
whatever we are whatever the bounds of
us as an identity is we're kind of
pockets of the universe where entropy is
decreasing but then there's nothing kind
of a prior stopping that process
expanding to let's say Societies or
worlds right or galaxies or milky ways
and and I guess the question is is
uh where where does the where does
what's the what's the overarching clo
system uhu because you know I again I
know you're this is this might not be
your the question that you want to
answer I don't mind waxing with your
thinking you know speculating if well
just seems to me that and again this is
not an argument from design I think
interestingly there seems to be a sort
of re Resurgence perhaps of an argument
from design I know Philip gfer just
released his book why which is um a kind
of philosophical argument for I wouldn't
say it's design per se maybe it is from
a S probabilistic
perspective um I think relying on
actually I won't I won't say because I
haven't had Philip on but um you know
the universe has it's it it has its
space at least for entropy
reduction but we still have to we still
have the second lamic thermodynamics
operating in these close
systems I guess the question I would ask
to a physicist is
what what if it's just open systems all
the way
up well yeah I would love to have be fun
to pair pair up with a physicist here
and ask literally that question um all I
will say in my non- physicist hat uh is
that at least when I was constructing
this framework with Carl at the and it'd
be fun to get Carl's thought on that as
well
but oh well you know future yeah future
call in the future but uh uh I I like to
think that there is some outer close
system and so I guess when I was writing
this in a perhaps ignorant way I was
thinking of the entirety of the universe
as the entire system right that is the
close system because um I thought you
were gonna ask a different question and
I I might I have an answer for that one
but uh which go ahead about Cosmic
bodies and all the other entities this
universe right um uh but but just to to
stick to your your your comment um I
think the entire universe is the close
system and that's where the entropy is
going up because you know you probably
have heard about uh at least it's I
believe it's still like more of a
physics theory but the evental heat
death of the universe right everything
indeed increasing heat increasing energy
uh Asim Isaac Asimov has written
wonderful stories about it right um and
so uh I thought of the entirety of the
universe and every other entity that is
in it some of them could be you know
living in that non-equilibrium steady
state but everything eventually is
tending towards the heat death of the
universe so the closed system there is
an outerbound I just haven't picked it
specifically and that's where a
physicists would be much more qualified
to draw that boundary the tiny question
that I was wondering because it set you
were almost walked yourself there which
was when you brought up
bodies and I'll even throw an electrons
in here too because uh I thought you
were going to say our Cosmic bodies
mortal computers our our electrons
mortal Compu um and I do have an answer
for that one it's not again I'm not
going to pretend that I have the
physicist answer but I think Carl has
actually eloquently addressed this again
in other discussions related to this
paper because someone did ask him well
is the moon cognitive right yeah they
would also you could argue following
certain Dynamics as well why didn't we
include other objects because we have
actually examples in the paper very
specific like these entities serve as
wonderful examples of mortal computers
we can chat about them if you like um
but I like how Carl said why does the
moon not necessarily think or at least
we wouldn't call it cognitive and he
talks about these Dynamics the the flow
right and you can decompose flow in
physics and again I'll put it in the
lightest interpret
so that way I don't maybe misspeak um
but you can decompose uh Dynamics
according to helm holtan decomposition
so there is something called solenoidal
flow or conservative flow and then
there's this thing called dissipative
flow or the random fluctuations as Carl
has mentioned and there the idea is that
uh random fluctuations uh that's the
stochasticity of any system that you
must deal with and when you get close to
Quantum which I am not a Quantum person
person but I understand that the random
fluctuations are so high the amplitude
of them that they dominate the Dynamics
right and so that's why in quantum
mechanics you specify things in terms of
probability distributions um but then as
you move all the way up in increas and
and Carl's also been very careful to
avoid saying space which is constant but
rather just the size of the objects that
we're consider as we get up to uh
macroscop miso macro and cosmological
scale because you mentioned scales
earlier um the idea is that the flow
becomes more dominated actually almost
entirely if not completely solenoidal
right which is this conservative Flow
It's Time dependent flow dependent on
the states because again I should
mention to when we're talking about flow
talking about the states of a system
right and they change with time
everything is dynamic and evolving um
and so uh the dissipative random
fluctuations get averaged out because as
you get bigger and bigger in scale you
average out fluctuations and the
amplitude goes down right so the as you
progressively get bigger you
progressively average out the noise to
the point where when you get to the
cosmic bodies oh going on in solenoidal
flow whereas a Quantum or the very very
M the small scales it's mostly
dissipative random fluctuations so how
does that connect back to Mortal
computation or cognition or sentience or
anything of that form well Carl has used
the phrase the Goldilocks regime yeah so
and we didn't write about it in the
paper but I thought it was a nice it's a
good thing to think about that there is
this regime of being big enough but not
too big and not too small you know
that's the goal theck regime right such
that you have a balance or you have a
combination of dissipative flow and
solenoidal flow because the idea is that
you need that dissipative flow in order
to minimize your variational free energy
the idea is that we need that Dynamics
we need something to be surprised to uh
Drive our continual self-id but you need
that solenoidal flow which by the
solenoidal flow can be like rotational
flow very like a Carl used another
example just because I I remember seeing
this and it's stuck in my mind about
water then flowing towards a drain or a
or an open plug and as it rotates around
it doesn't go down that would be the
dissipative part it's going down the
gradient just the circular rotational
movement right so that's what you know
these bodies at the cosmic scale they
collapse to Newtonian or lran mechanics
or classical mechanics right and the
ideaas that they're just following this
conservative flow but there's no
dissipative random fluctuations whereas
electrons and Quantum objects as well
right they're just dealing with all this
dissipative extreme noise or
stochasticity so electrons don't think
uh and the moon does not think because
again you need sort of this balance
between these two Flows In order to uh
essentially uh promote this self-evident
in a structured way too because again if
everything is just so completely random
uh it's you know obviously hard to form
you know uh what is it steady patterns
and you oh and the other component to
this is the cycle and that's where I
think the Mortal part comes into play
the solenoidal flow or the rotational or
the predictable patterns or the
conservative patterns that's where you
get things that repeat heat or a
periodic and so that's what gets you the
life cycle so in there's a lot of
wonderful examples like breathing is
actually an example of that solenoidal
flow or Cycles in language or the fact
that you and I die right and there's the
cycle of death and rebirth um those
Cycles are more of that conservative
flow uh and that's the part what makes
creates this mortality right and that
mortality the other take by the way I
sort of skipping around a bit the other
motivation for Mortal computation is
that that cycle that life cycle adds a
pressure to these entities right that
would not normally be there because
again if you're Immortal and you don't
have to worry about death you might act
a different way right so that that life
cycle thing comes from that other aspect
of the flow but again when you get but
you need that sort of stochasticity
right to you know engender that
continual self- evidencing that wouldn't
be happening like the cosmic scale which
is just essentially all those random
fluctuations are averaged out so I think
uh you didn't ask that question per se
but you almost and I thought you were
GNA yeah thought I should answered that
because I think that's something that's
not really addressed in the paper and I
was surprised to see a couple different
places that that question comes up so no
electrons don't think and the moon does
not think at least in accordance to the
way we were thinking about Mortal
computation there is possibly a
Goldilocks regime but what are the
bounds of those regim I I I'm not sure
yeah yeah yeah no I in in the first
episode of this podcast Carlo and I go
quite deep into that oh see on that
already okay yeah well it it goes It
goes pretty you know we start talking
about information geometry spaces and um
and indeed these flows yeah yeah so so
just for everyone um Co does a big
exposition of that in the first episode
and and yeah it's beautiful because it
ties together as well like this what
I've been speaking about with
phenomenologists especially people
interested in haiger this kind of future
orientated nature that we have because
we're always at risk of being dispersed
so we always have to be acting for our
self organization not only at time T but
also for t plus one yeah which which
feeds into this kind of notion of Al
estasis so we've we've done we've done a
huge Cosmic overview without even
talking about the paper but I do want to
ask one more question about Immortal
computation going all the way back to
what versus Mortal computation going all
the way back to what we were talking
about at the beginning so the the way
that Jeff so Jeff Jeffrey Hinson super
important guy in machine learning um and
I know him and Carl and P Diane there's
you know they were working together in
the 90s so this is a very long history
Gatsby Union right yeah yeah yeah at the
Gatsby exactly um and you know this
casting of immortal versus Mortal as
being a software Hardware dichotomy so
in Mortal computation the software is
kind of bound to the hardware like us
right at least the way that we would uh
you know most materialists would think
of cognition and the Brain whereas
software is um substrate independent in
the sense that you can take something
like chat gbt and put on my computer put
it on your computer um so that in my
mind again because I'm coming at this
from a philosophical perspective makes
me think of functionalism as a kind of
philosophical theory of mind which at
least in its kind of very raw form is
substrate independent and an argument
which comes from NED block which is a
kind of argument add obso is that um if
you take that idea of substrate
Independence seriously what you might
end up with is what he called the
Chinese brain which is let's replace
every let's have a let's have a system
where every neuron in the brain is
replaced with a person from China
because the number of neurons in a
certain brain region you know map onto
the number of people in China and if
they do all the flagging right if they
do like the synaptic
integration then we would have to be
compelled if it was completely
isomorphic
to say that that brain was um was
conscious and he goes well this is just
clearly wrong and now you have you do
have functionalist who will say well
actually that brain would be conscious
sorry that Chinese Nation would be
conscious I guess I say all of this to
ask you know just purely on intuition
does the notion of a kind of boundlessly
immortal comput uh computer in or or or
software really does that really make
sense because it seems to me that yes
you can access TR gbt and I can access
track gbt but that is contingent on the
fact that you and I are working on at
least relatively similar Hardwares MH um
so I'm wonder I'm just wondering whether
the notion of immortal software is
itself a slight red herring or an
overshoot possibly um I mean I I
guess I guess the way to think about
what the argument for Immortal
computation really says right is that um
well
so I gotta think this one through
because yeah I've not heard about you
know the the actual problems with
Immortal computation per se
so are are you are you referring to
maybe perhaps the limitations of it well
just I I'm just kind of bringing into
question the very you know the very
dichotomy that is supposedly at the
heart of the problem which is that you
you have hardware systems that are
uh prey to dissipative forces whether
it's the metal in my laptop or the
Silicon or whatever it is and then you
have the software which which arguably
is substrate independent right that mean
that's the very dichotomy that's set up
my point
is is it the in the substrate
Independence is is a bit of a misnomer
it's not necessarily the case because
all the all the evidence we have for
substrate Independence are relying on
very similar substrates right like we
all have very similar I see you're
saying that because at the end of the
day we are effectively using the same
type of substrate right you and I
executing this so the fact that we
aren't we aren't really testing the the
independence component right running it
on an entirely different substrate write
it on a write it on the population of
China and see right like you said create
the uh chin chese room style the system
right could we that could we construct
that um possibly I mean it is possible
that it is a misnomer um I guess maybe
what people think about and again you
could probably even find minor
criticisms or minor issues with this is
like when you change the particulars of
the hardware so you know when we run for
example chat gbt or Transformer we're
using something like a g U System right
you know maybe multiple gpus well I
could say well wouldn't changing the
hardware mean I run it on a set of let's
say I have a lot of CPUs lying around
right that is different Hardware they
have similar properties like let's say
physical properties in silico right um
but they are different constructs to run
you know the same thing and the idea is
that um you know Chad gbt would run just
fine on a set of CPUs to my knowledge I
haven't necessarily tested it but you
can run multi CPU systems
same thing with a TPU they might just
have different speeds right they give
you maybe uh the speed of training the
convergence properties might change but
at the same time they will again if
we're not doing learning I would imagine
the program runs the same way and I
would even imagine that you can run
let's say you had a really really good
like device that isn't a multi-gpu
system you pre-trained your model and
now you run it on there it'll behave
roughly the same however I could the
argument that even then there's going to
be differences right because there the
the properties of just the actual system
that you're simulating on you can even
talk about for example seed generation
so you know when we write a program we
have a computer seed right you control
the do the noise or you control the
level of determinism in your computer
simulation and uh you can use wall clock
time for example to generate seeds well
if you change the system well you're not
going to have access to the exact
properties that instan sated that seed
on my computer so already your
computer's on a different stochastic
trajectory if it let's say uses noise I
mean maybe Transformers might not be the
ultimate best example but any system
that's like a noisy neural model would
already be behaving a little bit
differently right you'd maybe on average
they would behave the same if we
averaged out those fluctuations um so
there is a little bit of difference
across Hardware platforms it could
possibly be a misnomer and again to use
your example of the uh the Chinese room
style neurons and we simulate GPT right
but with these particular with humans
serving as those neurons um yeah I would
I I don't know if I can really comment
on whether or not he would that could
perhaps be a way to break the uh
complete immortality of the system um I
think what moral computation just to
make sure that I uh don't get lost in
the plot here is that mortal computation
really really wants to emphasize that uh
at the end of the day
well the way that we design our programs
they really are Eternal I mean they
might not necessarily run exactly the
same like you're pointing out there
there could be some problems but we are
not designing our intelligence systems
with any uh or very little uh what do
you call it constraint or
informed informative information about
the substrate it's going to run like
when I write my neural simulation I run
it on a server maybe I run it on my
desktop I don't think about oh is this
device actually going to affect the
characteristics of my program like
that's sort of what Mortal computation
even touches on which is like the
particular quirks of an entity are very
substr it's like almost like once you
build one particular neuro robot you
would also get what in cognitive science
there's this term coming up cognitive
diversity right so if I built a
different neuro robot bot let's say I it
has very similar structure right you
would say okay well these two mortal
computers I I tried to design them
exactly the same I run the same program
well because they are two separate
entities and the way they interact with
their environment they are going to have
their own e eccentricities their own
quirks their own particular Knowledge
from self- evidencing them particular
selves right so the idea is that this
neur robot this neur robot while they
have very similar Hardware style they're
still going to two very different
systems whereas Chad GPT which was let's
say or Transformer let's not pick on
Chad GPT but any of these big neural
models that was let's say pre-trained
and then you know Consolidated and said
I'm going to clone you into these
systems maybe their inference system
right their inferences might lead them
to uncover different data but at the end
of the day the particularities and
quirks of the software came they're kind
of tied to the same origin point right
so um I think that amount of adapt ity
in the essence of how we again find
ourselves towards the NES the
non-equilibrium steady state is really
dictated by that particular knowledge
and information that's encoded in your
body and so that's where we can touch on
and I know you're familiar with the
embodiment thesis or embodied cognition
I think that's the other part to Mortal
computation that's important is that the
body offloads some of this cognition
whereas again even in the the Chinese
room version of Chad GPT or whatever uh
we're not necessarily using uh nonb
sorry bodily non-neural like components
to sort of offload this cognition so
that separation that that uh blending
and that combination is not there in
those types of systems so perhaps that's
where I think maybe I just want to
remind that we The Immortal computation
really refers to that entanglement right
that design co-design of the software
with the hardware the substrate and the
uh you know the intelligent algorithm
that you're designning if that makes
sense nice yeah yeah that makes perfect
sense and yeah it it brings in
embodiment very nicely
um yeah so let let's go into our
triple stasis words Asis I don't know
where the limit stops so I think people
will be aware of what homeostasis is
it's this you know this description of
the fact that uh biotic organisms have
certain bounds
that they have to retain you know remain
within in order for their survival to be
viable so you know we actually all learn
this at school but you can think of
glucose levels or you can think of
temperature something a bit more foreign
to people is allostasis which is
actually quite simple it's just the idea
that uh uh you cognizers capable of more
uh you greater temporal planning can
take prospective action to minimize
future homeost you know homeostatic
problems so if it if I look outside of
my window and I see it snowing I can
plan in advance and put on a coat before
I go because I know if I go out there
I'm GNA have these dis homeostatic
outcomes because I'm going to freeze to
death right so but you know maybe uh my
dog although they love the you know
actually my dogs they love the snow they
don't really mind but let's say they did
they might freeze to death actually they
probably wouldn't but you know the bound
yeah it's fuzzy who has what yeah yeah
but then you introduced this third term
uh you and
Carl
homeis thank you homeorhesis
yeah to get it to say it right too
wonderful homeorhesis homeorhesis yeah
um let's just start with what does that
mean sure um so the really simple way to
think about it so that way those that
are familiar with homeostasis so you
could you could State homeostasis as
there's a set point or a particular
there's kind of flavors of it a number
an average number or a range that you
want to keep like your temperature again
so that way we avoid leaving the
non-equilibrium steady state and dying
um so we want to keep things within a
range and we want to keep things
relatively constant right that's what
homeostasis ultimately says um and then
you built on it allostasis is predictive
homeostasis right it's trying to serve
homeostasis to prevent that hormesis one
way you could take it is it's time
varying homeostasis so that's the the
first place you could move to which is
what if that set point was changing with
time right it was dynamical so in that
sense that that almost gets you roughly
to hormesis a better way to so that
that's one way to build on the
audience's knowledge another way to
state hormesis is that instead of it
being like you or a process returns to a
set point or constant value or within a
range you are returning to a trajectory
so that's it's where it's like it's a
random dynamical systems view of
homeostasis whereas homeostasis is
talking about con a return to a constant
Point here we are returning to a
trajectory so this that's the time
Evolution and I think that to me made
more sense so I'd say that would be
hormesis and then by the way a fun
variation to it and again you won't find
these too common around is horo hetic if
you want to say something is homeostatic
you would also say homeo hetic or a
homeo process try saying that a few
times that's yes I think I think Cole
just proves as the dictionary and just
manages
to it is amazing it is amazing um okay
that's really interesting because so
again this is this is kind of converging
with a LW the reading that I've been
doing I've been TR ring back through
Andy Clark's work um and he has a
wonderful wonderful paper called
knitting your own Markov blanket yeah
yeah yeah which is fantastic and he
talks about how and I think this is a
reasonable uh critique that was
leveraged at the free energy principle
and act of inference in its original
Inception is that it kind of took the
mark of blanket as a fixed uh
statistical entity let's say um and
therefore the particle the internal
States and the external States it didn't
really allow for you know dynamical the
the unfolding of dynamic what dynamical
system theory predicts which are
trajectories as you said so uh Andy
Clark says well let's take less of a
substantial ontology and think more of
process ontologies so in the same way as
a butterfly you know is not the same
thing through the course of its lifespan
we can still identify the butterfly
through a process
ontology now there's a really
interesting part of your paper that you
know this actually I'm really glad that
we we touched on this because you say a
morphogenetic system from a cybernetics
point of view is one that maintains its
continuity and integrity by altering
essential aspects of its organization
and or structure and I thought this was
just like really interesting because no
one I think could have expected the word
altering there right they would have
thought that continuity and integrity is
going to be the maintenance of its
organization and structure so I written
here at what point does a morph genetic
system change its identity and what is
the distinction between identity and
organization so we can because we can
have as you say on the Arc of a lifespan
on the trajectory we have different
points in which we can say
self-organization according to this
statistical Dynamics is happening but 10
years later there's a whole different
scope of self-organization but it's
still self-organizing that process is
still going on but we don't want to call
these these two distinct entities right
the caterpillar and the Butterfly or the
baby and the adult because there seems
to be some Integrity or continuity to
use your
language is that Just an Illusion right
um you know I I I come from this from uh
The Works of people like Derek parfett
who say that well there is no single
substantial self it's psychological
continuity but in a sense you can almost
bracket that psychological continuity
off again we're talking about lens of
analysis and say okay well that's the
system yeah that's the self right that's
what that's what
matters in the same way you can say okay
we're no longer really concerned about
the difference between the uh
caterpillar and the Butterfly what we're
talking about is the fact that butterfli
follow because of genetic reasons this
path and we can identify the path now as
what a butterfly caterpillar is so all
of that to
say how do you resolve this tension
between identity and organization
because it seems to capture reality we
really do have to integrate this
dynamism and this in this these flows
over time and these
changes wonderful example um the
butterfly in the caterpillar I think
it's Andy's um yeah I've read that
somewhere too I Know Carl refers to it
in one of his works as well it's
probably Andy I don't I don't know um so
there's a lot to imp hack there but the
one concept I'll just say to start
before I forget it is that the butterfly
and the caterpillar example you'd say
well okay are they different right you
know I consider that and this is where
again since we did start earlier with
hormesis which was returning to a
trajectory rather than returning to a
constant value you can sort of borrow
that idea of time evolving systems and
just saying that uh the fact that that
butterfly is a projection or a
continuation of that caterpillar's
identity the fact that Evolution that
change is the the uh caterpillar
caterpillar butterfly system yeah yeah
yeah that is the one object and um so
that's kind of like that that Evolution
and I do think I touch on it in here in
in some way or another about that that
changes you right that that
Evol because again because we are
ohic your your uh the variables and the
right critical ranges and things will
change with time as well you'd say well
wait aren't you aren what aren't all
organisms defined by this very specific
set point the idea is that you have to
remember you are an open system and you
live in an environment that itself
changes with time so the idea is that
because that is evolving as well and and
also it's changing because of you you're
you remember we talked earlier about
Niche Construction uh we are acting and
changing our environment so we need to
constantly be changing um so that
evolutionary process I think of as is
your identity and I I could have swore
it might have been Andy or Carl in
reference to Andy or someone that was
referring to his work about that there
you can look at metamorphosis as still
that that is part of your it's also part
of your identity preservation because
it's like an adaptation right an
adaptivity to a Time evolving universe
um you also asked earlier so to make
sure I connects so that's the the the
simple answer is that I still see the
the butterfly as the caterpillar it's
just not called a caterpillar it's a
it's the identity is still there but the
structural form has been right in part
of that trajectory that so the cat and
again the we could also say caterpillars
generally always end up metamorphing
into a butterfly there is a trajectory
so that is distinct that is that
particular insect right right same thing
with a human has a different trajectory
in same you you could use your favorite
animals like your dogs you mention your
dog earlier you know was a puppy right
puppy the same as the full grown dog
well there was a trajectory it was the
growth growth is part of the Mortal
computation framework and we did make
sure to put that in there uh and there's
different ways to characterize growth
regeneration and Decay uh in death um uh
but you said earlier about I identity
and
organization um so I want to be a little
careful because there's also the world
of I am familiar with philosophy of mind
but I don't want to get too much in
there and start angering philosophers
we've already probably angered a little
bit with our ignorance on physics so not
try to step on too many toes but so the
way I thought about it in Mortal
computation is there's this idea of
organization and structure you did bring
up morphism so this will help connect
all those parts for the audience that
heard these words um and I think of them
as sort of two different complementary
things uh and then I'll tell you where
identity comes into this picture so uh
organization in from a self-organizing
dynamical systems kind of cybernetics
perspective is the relation the parts
and the relationships between them right
and so uh a human might say you could
say well okay we have two arms and two
legs and we are organized according to
this way our cells are arranged in a you
know have certain relationships to each
other structure is the instantiation of
the organization it is that specific you
darus are very different than me uh in
your instantiation in this universe
right uh you and I are both humans right
we both have rough organization of Parts
um but our physical embodiment our
actual you know instantiation into this
moment in time uh is that organization
expressed right in a biological form but
again you could talk about as in silico
entities as well and so the nice thing
about thinking about organization and
this is where again like that that idea
of like uh organizational closure we use
that in our definition as well as long
as you have sort of these arrangement of
parts and these relationships between
them right and it's very abstract it's
kind of like it doesn't want to tell you
exactly what you need to create to
create this for example animal um that's
the identity right it is these rough
relationships so that's where I want to
I I don't particularly divorce the idea
of the identity that organiz rough
organization of parts and I say rough
because you know again we can we think
of it as an evolving trajectory as well
the structure itself is different and
that's what's kind of nice is that
changes on a a a faster time scale if
anything else so the fact that you and I
started as babies and we are now adults
right that is because cells are growing
cells are being born cells are dying
there's also pre-programmed cell or
sorry programmed cell death
potosisd from the environment and it's
also saying okay well I want to repair
that damage and that's where the
morphogenetic morphogenesis kind of
Concepts come into play is you and I I
think a better example you can even
think about neurons in the brain uh
neurons you know live for a certain time
scale synapses live on a much less time
scale many synapses die and within so
many you know minutes or seconds and
cells die every but then they're grown
and reborn so you and I are no longer
the same exact collection of cells that
we were a few days ago we are different
uh physical embodiment yet you're still
darus your identity is still roughly
there even if maybe you have a few more
cells right and more you you're growing
and adapting to your environment so I
think that's an important kind of
concept is to think about the difference
between organization and structure
they're not actually the same thing
which again if you don't not familiar
with that distinction you might assume
well aren't I the same structure uh no
you're not that's kind of like the the
actual component the physical substrate
itself is in a constant process of death
and birth and repair and damage and uh
even the processes themselves and at
some point or another in the paper we
talk about that even the processes of
repair are repairing themselves or
decaying so there's this Con so this is
where again allthough all that blabbing
that I just did goes back to again that
trajectory right you are a trajectory
rather than a fixed set of things that
need to maintain them exactly as they
were because you're dissolution into the
environment is that trajectory no longer
being there right that you're not able
to actually maintain your hormesis which
is returning to that and I like hormesis
is is such a great word because it
really just reflects the idea of what we
said earlier the non-equilibrium steady
state right we always want to return to
that but that state right whatever that
might be to uh ensure your continued
organization your continued identity is
changing with time right because the
conditions the environment are changing
you are in a naturally evolving system
just by basis of you yourself acting on
it so everything is constantly evolving
so I guess there might be a tension I
have and perhaps I entered the the the
chat entered the discussion late enough
that uh I don't see I don't see a
problem with the metamorphosis I see
that as that is the fact that you are
your you are a trajectory and so yeah
entity still continues it's just your
physical structure might be different
right and that explains growth um there
is one final tiny point I'll add to it
so uh and I got to be careful where the
where I use the word so when we were
talking about the cybernetics it's funny
how biophysics and cybernetics they sort
of have similar word different words for
the same kind of concept uh I think that
uh yeah that that's a t almost tological
kind of way of you know viewing it but
um one thing that they have in
cybernetics is called
self-replication uh which is what we
used in the cybernetics back end of the
Mortal computer in this paper to explain
that uh you know systems will uh produce
more of those parts they organize and
you can think of them as cells growing
or dying um and if you add mutation to
the self-replication you get
reproduction so that is where you get
this concept of okay well what if for
example you have Offspring you know one
day you know you have a a daughter or a
son um and they they are a continuance
also of your identity in a way right
because they are still subject to all
the conditions that you were subject to
right they still need to find their
non-equal ibrium steady state they need
to preserve their organizational closure
their identity uh with an evolving
structure or Mor phological
instantiation right but in a way your
identity is carried on through them and
then Carl had this really nice uh uh it
was in again one of those interviews he
had in the past of that it's also a way
of getting what's called optimal basan
forgetting where as you get older you
get more set in your ways you become
wide but you're less able to change and
so that's the the cycle part The
evolutionary Evolution's kind of answer
to saying that okay you are not adapting
as well as you could or as effectively
because the optimal thing would be is
you say okay let me start over let me
and this would be related to like your
neural information but you know let me
start over again well you kind of can't
right you you have continuously
self-evidence to a point that uh things
are more easily predictable for your
internal generative model which is you
know one way of looking at your your
identity uh and you you are now kind of
rigid you're less likely to change you
have certain charistics that you've
established right so that's why you have
Offspring and then you have you know
your the Next Generation and they don't
have the same constraints they're more
flexible they're more plastic they're
more able to change whereas you were
less able to however your identity still
continues it might not continue directly
obviously you know if you have let's say
a sun not EX they're not darus but they
have elements of you in there right you
know the things that you interacted with
them the knowledge that you imparted
with them so you could even think of I'm
I'm going a little a little beyond the
rails here of the paper but we do touch
on just like reproduction is just the
mutated self-replication concept and you
know once you have that you know that's
how you preserve your identity and
project it even further into the future
in a somewhat more abstract way um I
also think and at risk of blabbing any
further I'll I'll stop here is that it
connects nicely to one of the other
motivations towards the beginning of the
paper uh we only briefly and I don't
want that to be kind of like a sticking
point touch on uh the philosophy of life
and death or existentialism which is a
lot broader and it touches on a lot of
other bigger Concepts than I think
mortal computation but we we borrowed
this idea the fact that and you said it
earlier as well the fact that oh you
because you brought up haiger and being
in t uh the fact that we know that there
is an end uh and that we project towards
the end we sort of act because of that
and that's where the I connect it back
to the reproduction we impart
information we teach right we express
ourselves through music or art um I
think it's a nice kind of cultural
connection uh from the idea of even
mortal computation which is that that's
how you pass on your knowledge you're
encoding your information in your
Offspring and giving them somewhat of a
prior right and then of course they'll
obviously adapt and you know can you do
their self- evidencing and modify their
posterior according to the data they
acquire from the environment but that's
your way your identity still carries on
in perhaps an indirect way but that's a
projection far beyond your own physical
end in death so I thought that was a
nice thing we did is that we touched on
that because there's naturalist
philosophy which is I think a little bit
closer to you know what motivates the
idea of moral computation but that
existentialism is kind of there under
the hood and you sort of realize well
okay that's why we act the way we do we
know that this isn't going to continue
forever which stands in stark contrast
to the artificial intelligence systems
that we have in today which in principle
they don't have a known end right they
could theoretically keep running being
copied on to a different sub so I think
I'll stop or at least yeah or at least
they wouldn't know right um I mean um
yeah I mean a whole a whole branch of of
therapy and philosophy Terror management
Theory erns Becka denial of death is
exact points exactly to what you're
saying which is that you we are
motivated by finality whether that's as
strong as ear specka that everything we
do is governed by the Spectre of death
you know we create works of art for a
legacy we have children so on I I like
the hiigaran view which is that there's
this very sort of subtle um future
orientation in all of our actions it
doesn't have to be as concrete as
creating a
masterpiece um but it's just the fact
that and this actually might point to
the incapacity for presentness in some
sense is that we always have to be
thinking even if it's implicit right
because self-organization is always for
t plus one because T's already been
taken care of you're there yeah right um
yeah yeah it's all really cool I love
that there's some really amazing work
that's being done on on existentialist
philosophy and active inference on hiar
and hle and stuff yeah yeah there was a
couple things that came to mind that I
think is worth contributing I think one
is uh a notion of philosophical
vagueness that's often forgotten which
is that some questions are just open
right at what point system a becomes
system b or or what point it retains its
Aus yeah Derek parfit who again I
mentioned is really influential he just
says it's an open question there is no
answer right you know it's it's uh feus
a ship or it's sores Paradox at what
point does the grain of sand the
accumulation of the grain of sand become
the Heap well depends on who you ask and
that's fine I mean it might just be our
our proclivity to have um binary results
right we just want a yes or a no the
other thing that came to my mind was
that yet you know we're talking a lot
here about change I guess the one thing
that remains is the the mechanism to be
able to say that you are a thing has to
be the same now whether you call that
self- evidencing or self-organization or
the fact that you are matching
operational closure with thermodynamic
openness or sense
making whether you're the whether you're
the caterpillar or the butterfly you're
still abiding by those laws and so I
think that's where Carl's stressing that
the free energy principle doesn't tell
you what's going to be there it doesn't
tell you what's going to be there now or
in the past or in the future it might
come to that because I know they're
doing things about scaling up Markov
blankets and and now we're having
Dynamic Mark of blankets and we Mark of
blankets but it's very raw form it just
tells you if something is here
now and if it's going to be there at t
plus one and we're going to say there
the same thing
axiomatically they must be minimizing
free energy just just on pure quite
boring maths and so it made me think
that like the but all of this stuff is
is hinges on the fact that there is some
level of self- evidencing going on so
the mechanism itself stays the same yes
so I thought that was yeah yeah so I
thought that was interesting all right
cool and you're still and you're still
interacting with your environment
through your Markov
blanket the the
morphological substrate instantiation of
it evolves with time you're still there
it's still a mark blanket you're still
interacting with sensory and active
States yeah yeah yeah yeah exactly
you're sense making but in the what's
what's cool about sort of Evan
Thompson's work and the inactive uh
tradition is that the the autop pesis is
is is also so it's not just that sense
Mak is happening but also Auto pesis is
happening it just depends on your scale
analysis right so you have cell autop
poesis as well as cell sense making but
that's embedded it's not it's not
distinct it's embedded within the
autopoetic sense making of a nervous
system which itself is doing sense
making because it's got act it's got
sensory motor uh relations going on yeah
so it's not just that this is you know
transformative of x to Y it's also it's
also recursive m mm that you could have
like a and b bracketed within a or what
you know whatever like it's it's like
language in many ways right we've just
got loads of relative clauses and you
know these are embedded Markoff blankets
um we also do that in the paper we also
have a I I don't know if you caught that
uh uh mortal computers within mortal
computers we had yeah yeah yeah C
subunit because I did talk about it in
yes yeah yeah yeah yeah and they one
mortal computer sets the set point of
another mortal computer computer so you
get that recursive beautiful
construction that you just mentioned
there you can have that in the framework
as well I like that yeah yeah yeah it's
wonderful um so I wanted to ask one more
kind of specific technical thing about
the paper and then a couple final more
you know more general questions sure I
thought this notion I'd never come
across before and I was really I really
liked it was cybernetic variety ah I
thought this was really cool and the law
of requisite variety I thought these
were really really
fascinating um additions to the paper by
the way for people wondering because you
know this is in the paper this is in the
paper the paper is big and bold and it's
got a lot in it and it has appendix too
and it has an appendix which I didn't
read um you didn't need you didn't need
to I no the paper's fantastic but yeah
it has a lot in it and I wanted to and I
really enjoyed this bit on cybernetic
variety so maybe just for our audience
if you could explain what that means me
sure uh and I remember too reading that
there was even in cybernetics confusion
as to what variety was but uh I think
the simplest way to look at it is that
it's the number of states in a in an
entire system so the cardinality of the
state spacee so uh in very specifically
it's actually the log base two of the
cardinality of the state space to give
it so uh we got to give uh so the thing
I we got to give Ross Ashby who's the
the author of things like the law of
requisite variety and the good regulator
theem actually one of the one of the
many uh core contributors to the field
of cybernetics we we gotta talk about
Weiner and the other wonderful guys that
were cyberneticist as well but um Ross
Ashby made some really wonderful
contributions and so variety effectively
is like I said the different number of
different states and I was thinking
about this last night in preparation for
this meeting just to remind myself so
one thing you can think of it is that
you have the number of distinct kind of
configurations and you could think of um
I'll use an example I think it's better
to explain it let's say you're trying to
debug um the fact that your light's not
turning on so you have one component you
could look at which is the light switch
and so it had light switch itself has
two states on or off so it's binary
right so the variety of that's actually
log base two of two which is one so
there's one difference or distinction
and that's one re that's where the word
variety I believe really gets um but no
one really quite says it except Ross
Ashby in his textbook you can find it
somewhat described in there um there's
one distinction between the on and the
off SE and that's by the way that is
variety right there and it's wholesale
but one way to think about you're trying
to debug why your light's not turning on
so you you identify
oh the problem is in the light switch um
so this will help us understand the law
of requisite variety you had uh you know
one controllable changeable aspect of
the environment which was one thing um
and you had one hypothesis or one kind
of uh thought internally about how to
fix that and so one you're you had
internal variety of one and the
environment ah yes I see where you're
going nice right just to help us connect
together variety is useful to understand
the cybernetic principles um okay so
that's great law the variet internal
variety was One external variety was one
now let's say that it wasn't the problem
the light switch is not the reason why
it's not broken so now you have to
figure out something else in the system
so there's also uh let's say I don't
know a battery or an internal component
that's really I'm not going to give us
the right Electronics engineering here
but there's another component that you
figure out ah it had an it's either
broken or not broken right it had these
two possible States or like let's say
it's um sorry it's it's either this or
it's that you figure out that was the
source of the problem well your variety
is two because it's a sum of these
independent components that make up the
system so it's you had two binary States
and you just sum up these independent
components that are not necessarily
we're going to act as if they are
directly uh jointly distributed they are
independent components you solve the
problem your internal variety was two
the external variety was two you solve
the problem because solving the problem
by the way is that you found stability
right you you fix the issue that you
don't want to be in a dark room right
that's kind of against your life right
that's sort of like you want you want
the room to be lit up so that was the
other thing and so then you could
continue extending this out and finding
chains of things that are problematic
and you keep summing up the log base two
of the number of distinct states that
these components have but let's say that
you just did those two and that wasn't
the problem and that's it those are the
only two things you can think of from
your internal model of the environment
you're like well there's a light switch
and I know there's a power source to
that light switch I've looked at both
those things they're not broken I fix I
I still have a dark room well th the
environment has greater variety than you
it has it turns out that if you had
known there's actually a power breaker
outside all you had to do was like flip
it on and off and you had on but you
never you never get to that so the
external variety is three but your
internal variety is two you have now
failed or you you are violating the law
of requisite Variety in the sense that
you are not going to be able to solve
your problem you won't survive and you
could then connect this problem solving
back to homeostasis or hesis where
you're trying to block or protect these
life critical variables or metabolic
variables which Ashby does talk about
them he doesn't maybe always call them
uh
meta metabolic things but he does use
the word homeostasis which is another
way of saying in cybernetics Ultra
stability which that you're able to very
quickly go back to that optimal
configuration or that good configuration
you have currently found and so so
that's like the law of requisite variety
and helping you define variety all at
once I think it's good to just connect
the two variety is useful though for
like a ton of other principles and I
think you probably you mentioned law of
requisit variety and the good regulator
theorem uh there's a lot of other and
there's even more there's a few others
that I didn't include in the paper um
about they're all driven by variety like
for example blind selection and
retention uh and order through noise
because this touches on I noticed uh
chaotic systems and random dynamical
systems there's a lot of relationships
and overlap between modern-day
cybernetics uh and those principles but
like the idea in terms of variety is
that there are all these states in the
environment and what you want to do is
you want to try to reduce that variety
you want to find configurations where
there is less variety because then that
will your ultimate goal and we uh Carl
and I sort of reframed a little bit
cybernetics it were reorganized it into
these pillars so one of them is what's
your goal which is you want Ultra
stability not just stability Ultra
stability which is their your ease in
which you can self-organize or get back
into that condition where again you're
internal variety is balanced to the
external variety you're able to con
continue your homeostasis you not going
to dissolve or disintegrate um the other
one that we had was uh what was it uh
regulation or was it no it was oh it was
growth sorry I gotta remember there were
three one is growth of course the idea
and cybernetics does talk about this is
where I said earlier about the principle
of self-replication there are two other
principles I just want to tag in there
the principle of autocatalytic growth
and the principle of recursive systems
which is that um you know the idea is
that once you start to find the right
resources right and assuming that there
are enough you're going to grow and grow
bigger and bigger and bigger because the
idea is that you want to preserve your
configuration you want to continue um
and then recursive systems just talks
about the fact that well these little
building blocks as they you know
stabilize into configurations and
replicate and you know you get more of
them they start to connect to each other
and this is how you get complex systems
right you can build heterarchical or
hierarchical systems and this gets into
Herbert Simon he wrote some nice papers
about this so you get more and this is
you could relate that to cells like for
example single cells organizing and
combining together create multicellular
structures which eventually give rise to
organs which give rise to subsystems and
gives rise to you know complex entities
like animals right yeah and then the
final part is regulation which we just
talked about uh law of requisite variety
uh and I should mentioned to like you
you want noise in this process this is
the other one of the other pillars that
helps us search through the space this
gets a little bit like reinforcement
learning for exploration you need noise
and then that's how you get order it's
called the signal to order uh principle
and then the final component is like you
said law of requisite variety the good
regulator theorem I don't know if you
wanted to make the audience clear on
that but it just basically says um in
order to be a controller of your
environment or something that controls
its environment is a model of its
environment refers to its internal
generative model and so in order to be
good at manipulating and doing Niche
construction right you need to have a
good internal generative model and what
better generative model than to be a
model of your environment or the world
you live in and then there's one last
one is called model of internal model
control or IMC principle uh I just
wanted to give that guy uh that
principle credit it's not fair sometimes
you see like oh it's only Ash beads like
no there are a lot of other wonderful
yeah yeah scientists there and that just
basically talks about U we talk about a
synthesis of a controller in environment
and we want to deem it to be uh stable
from what's called a closed loop point
of view um because that's where feedback
is introduced and so there's this
basically just an extension of like the
good regulator theorem uh I'm trying to
remember his name this is what makes me
feel bad because I wanted to highlight
his principle but he worked actually
with ashb on the good well good
regulator is Conan and ashb yeah Conan
that's the other name I wanted and he
had another principle the model
principle internal model control which
just talked about uh you want uh stab
you want it to be structurally stable
from a closed loop perspective and that
that's another component that you would
like in your system so I think with all
that that gives you your definition of
variet that's that's nice I gotta get
more into my cybernetics um wonderful
yeah yeah really cool it may there there
are several things that popped into my
head there I mean one is I think there's
a really nice uh mapping between the law
of requisite variety and basian
inference in the sense that to be able
to conduct a posterior I need my States
and I need to conduct okay what's the
probability of the state given an
observation but that itself is making
the inference that that state is there
in the world so I have to have a kind of
isomorphism between the states in my
generative model and the states I know
or or My expected States and the states
are in the world that said something
that I was thinking
is going back to our conversation about
entropy and again I'm not going to annoy
the the physicists but as I reduce my
internal variety I'm bringing entropy
down which thermodynamically means that
I have to be introducing some variety in
the environment yeah yeah so I think
what's interesting there is I think it's
just in the term and I think it's very
clever term law of requisite variety
it's not like the law of identical
variety because I have to have enough
that I can do uh you know sufficient
tracking of the environment but that
doesn't mean that um like that that is
like sufficient that I have enough but I
you where am I going with this you know
where I'm going with this um I was F
yeah yeah yeah I W I lost myself but in
the sense that yeah as I bring it
doesn't mean that the the external
system and the internal system are
always the same because it just depends
on sort of your again everything comes
back to the kind of lens of
analysis you might be causing entropy
elsewhere but you just need enough
variety so that you can account for your
little niche over here exactly I think
that's I got there I got there I got
that no I was F I thought that's where
you were going because it was talking
about like your local environment where
you right exactly because you're not all
over the
universe exist in this as we said
earlier in our least offensive way the
entire universe is the complete closed
system so that's what allows us to uh be
happy and uh and reconcile the second
law of Thermodynamics but you and I
while we are in the entire universe we
actually really care about and we are
working and operating in this very local
component of the right right local Eco
we're not everywhere on the planet
because you know that's we could talk
about the collective but just about you
and I think that's what you were where I
think you were going and that is your
law of requisite righty really respond
is really about your local Eco Niche
related to you at this moment en time
yeah exactly exactly we're not talking
about the variety of the entire universe
precisely precisely so yeah I guess the
optimal thing is just to dump my entropy
elsewhere and just run back to my bed
you know exactly throw that inop away
yeah yeah throw that iny away okay cool
that's really good I just wanted to uh
ask I guess a very theoretical question
which I think is a kind of yes or no
which is that if so with your I thought
your light bulb example was really
really useful if let's say uh so there
are multi so in terms of the external
variety let's say there are multiple
binary things that might be causing the
light bulb to not be working so the
switch the battery the fuse whatever but
I get it right the first time but I've
only got the knowledge of the thing that
I got right the first time so let's say
it's I I go for the battery and I think
oh I don't know anything about light
bulbs I'm four years old I only know
about batteries let me go look at the B
oh it was the battery was dead right has
the four-year-old in that example
like what what are they intelligent it's
a kind of um it's a kind of GTI problem
I'm not sure whether you're aware of Geo
problems Geo was a edman g was a French
philosopher I believe who basically
since Plato knowledge was defined as
Justified true belief so um how do I
know it's rainning well I can look
outside and I believe that it's raining
it's true that it's raining and I have a
Justified belief it's raining because I
can see that it's raining but if let's
say my cursons were closed
and I said and it was raining and do I
know that it's raining I say it's
raining I believe it's raining but I'm
not justified in my belief so get so
that was kind of since Plato what people
thought knowledge was edman Geer comes
up and basically says for example it's
like the same way that a clock is right
two time a wrong clock is right two
times a day I can look at that clock and
it might be accidentally true that it's
that time but is it is Justified because
I'm using a clock it's true and I
believe it but do I know that it's that
time because I've looked at that clock
well see so that's the philosophical
background um I can't really remember
where I was going with this oh yeah but
the the foury old who's got less who is
not obeying the law requisite variety
who's got minimum uh fewer sort of
internal States than the actual
volatility in the external world how
does cybernetics deal with that
individual so I mean at that moment in
time right you have less your internal
variety is less than external variety So
you you're in trouble but the component
that I at least where I'm going for is
that we're we're forgetting too that
there's an evolution and time adaptation
right to the system so that foure at
that moment failed to identify the
problem but that doesn't mean that they
can't explore and like you said earlier
I think you gave me sort of a piece of
the answer you said well they look up
batteries or you looked up a battery and
you learned how that works you might
later learn about the circuit breaker so
the LA cyber ICS you got to understand
that you are in the process of reducing
your variety and so you are changing
your configuration so the the
configuration or changing your state
means that earlier principle I mentioned
the the principle of uh order from noise
I think is important because it always
tells you we are trying to find
attractors in our state space right it's
an optimization problem and we want to
find an attractor or a pullback
attractor is what people say where it's
like something you like which again
connects nicely to Ness but without
repeating ourselves uh you are trying to
find these attractors and to reach again
like I said your ultimate goals Ultra
stability you want to be really good at
solving this light problem you want to
understand your generative model sorry
you want to understand your world which
requires you to update your generative
model there's a learning component an
evolving adaptivity process and that's
where like the good regulator theorem
says well you know you if you're a good
controller of your environment you're a
model of that environment but you might
not start out that way you need to adapt
you need to acquire information so
exploration and exploitation is actually
in cybernetics even though you know we
typically nowadays think oh that's just
the reinforcement learning concept no
they talked about exploitation which is
I like my particular tractor I'd like to
stay there and it's not very easy to
leave it however that noise is what
pushes us out and learns to find a
better configuration there is also some
other principles in the law of requisite
variety The Law of asymmetric
transitions which says that you are very
it's less likely for you to go from a
lower variety area to a higher variety
area um so that means we're always
looking for those spaces where we have
less variety and again we could use what
you and I discussed earlier your local
Eco Niche you want to find such that you
have the least amount of intern external
variety so that way you can match it
right to satisfy the law of requisite
variety um but the other part is the
order to noise principle and then
there's uh the The Selective retention
principle and I'm going to mess these up
even though I made sure to carefully
outline all of them in the paper so I do
recommend to read that to see their
their interrelated uh components but the
idea is that selective retention and
blind uh and blind selection is the idea
that you're more likely to stick to
better configurations or states that you
find in your optimization process but
that means you have to be changing you
have to leave where you currently are
especially if it's a very if it's a
suboptimal configuration so I think that
four-year-old that you talked about
earlier will eventually I mean it might
be a little difficult for you know in
this practical example to figure they're
going to figure out what a circuit
breaker is but maybe they're looking up
things on the internet they're learning
things about Electronics because they're
like I really don't want a dark house
and they're not going to just give up
let's assume that they're going to want
to tend because they want to survive in
the light represents the survival
they're going to learn about the circuit
breaker and so ultimately they are
evolving to a different configuration
that now they have a better generative
model of their environment or it's more
close to the actual environment right
because this was a factor a causal
factor that they just hadn't identified
but once you learn about that circuit
breaker now that's back into your system
now you understand its amount of states
and now you can match the external
variety of your local Ecco Niche or the
components of the local Ecco Niche that
are related to the problem you're trying
to solve because I think we could
probably cut up the niche in different
ways and say have different goals like
the light only requires these pieces of
the environment the other parts are not
relevant to this problem so we don't
have to even account like you we said
earlier for that variety we only need
the variety that's related to the
circuit breaker and you just need to
uncover through intelligent exploration
which connects back now we can even say
oh that justifies active inference we
need to actively sample our environment
so that we you can learn more about how
the electronic system works so that way
you can turn the lights back on does
that make sense very much so it was
thank you for doing the active inference
spin I was going to do it
um we're maximizing our basium surprise
we're we're doing our K divergences
between our prior and posteriors about
future States but no you it's fine um
but no very good exactly um it's not it
can't all just be pragmatic value there
are epistemic affordances that we need
to not exploit but we need to access um
to to be self- evidencing and that's all
in the equations for people who are
wondering um for that that K has derived
in terms of expected free energy in this
case excellent okay so we're coming up
to two hours I've got a couple final
questions one is
very uh well you can take it as long as
short as you want but I I was just
interested to see I've I've taken this
habit of when I read papers I love
reading the reference list um because
you know how they have numbers so you
know you either put the names or you put
the numbers and I love looking at the
numbers and you have a lot of numbers in
yours and I couldn't help but stumble
across um Donald Hoffman uhuh I don't
know if that was you or Carl um let me
just look at what the title was because
I
did it would have been his what's it
called
um oh I can't remember what the name of
his paper is in any case it doesn't
really matter um it's just he has a very
funky theory about what reality is um
and I anyone who knows about Donald
Hoffman I have to ask about Donald
Hoffman but
let's skip that then um final question
is there's a big hubub would say sorry
not steal your thunder here but yeah
because it says the interface theory of
perception right so uh can you briefly
remind me because I feel like I that'll
help trigger why I included him in the
referee yeah yeah so Hoffman has this
idea that we are evolved there's
multiple points of convergence here but
basically that we're evolved not for a
veridical perception but for survival
and so what we actually perceive is not
what's really out there but what but
Fitness payoffs and what he says is so
that's not particularly controversial
you have that in indirect realism you
know you have that going all the way
back to bur and Russell and even prior
but way what what becomes sort of
radical about Hoffman as he says well
time and space itself are part of that
interface and he derives a lot of this
from theories of physics where he says
okay now physics modern physics I
believe the no in 2022 was one for
something along this area um is showing
that there are these symmetries outside
of space and time he has these extremely
funky Greek derived names um which I
won't even try and pronounce and he's
very popular on um in in Academia and in
popular Academia so whenever I see his
name come up because I you know read his
book and I'm interested in his work I I
like asking people but in any case it
does it doesn't the first component of
what you explained is why
least I
remember I Know Carl and I had different
references but I remember that
resonating with the survival component
of the argument that's probably the
piece of his work that we thought
resonated in this work not the other I
don't have anything to say about the
other part although I should dig a
little bit further and see if there
might be something that changes but well
there he's got plenty of podcasts out
there and his book is very good what's
it called anyway you you know his name
on go it's all
um so the final thing I wanted to ask is
a kind of more broad sociological thing
which is that there's a huge hubbub
going on at the moment about AGI
artificial general intelligence and the
fact that you know Sam Alman came out
and said that um neuronet or large
language models are not going to get us
there and I think people have thought
that people have had their suspicions
since the 90s since inactive uh you know
in activist cognition for E cognition
because where are you action perception
Loops right whereas your grounding in
the world and so on and so then we have
a company like versus which is trying to
implement active inference uh
intelligence into you know in
silico just as a computer scientist I
can't help but ask you you know what do
you think is going to be the
trajectory um and do you think mortal
computation in the form of active
inference is going to get us there
oh this is a this is a good one and I I
feel like I should be a little careful
with my answer because there's that not
with you but there there's politics in
yeah about what we think might be the
future
um uh so I guess I'll say one thing
about the paper because the paper does
sort of touch on this right it actually
has a section towards the end that talks
about um the need to reconsider the path
of machine intelligence I think you may
remember we talk so Carl and I mention
in there uh about tool Centric AI um so
in that regard just from the broader
perspective without I I'll decouple the
versus thing in just a minute and I'll
address the active inference component
um while I don't know if mortal
computation is the only path I I we do
say it's one possible viable stepping
stone to a different path and I do think
it's a a Recon consideration of how we
build intelligence systems and I think
that that that's kind of it's another so
even though it's a survey right because
it's trying to survey all these
wonderful ideas from brilliant thinkers
and
Engineers uh theoreticians and engineers
and scientists over across all these
different domains um that we're trying
to say this Echoes a direction that we
want to build our our our adaptive
systems right and we don't have that
right now I mean we might we do have the
what do you call flickers of it and uh
the other piece I just want to point to
the audience is towards the end we give
examples of what we would consider
viable mortal computers that are not
even necessarily all in silico Ross
Ashby does deserve a little more love
and attention he has the homeostat which
we actually have a little pseudo
taxonomy and we call that a homeostatic
mortal computer although it can kind of
be allostatic depending on uh the later
uh Innovations other scientists made on
his homeostat um but we also talk about
these biotic uh mortal computers like
fungal systems we talk about uh
organoids which even though I haven't
had the pleasure to work with them I'm
deeply fascinated by or the sentient
organoid as uh Carl has called them in
snova and those that have done this
wonderful microphysiological
construction of these little entities
that can play Atari even if it's for a
short time span it's still fascinating
to me uh that we can use stem cells to
do this um also we got to get Michael Le
some wonderful attention we celebrate
the xenobot and the xenobot Swarm which
can do these wonderful things so I think
those are examples of the type of
intelligence that we would want to
strive to emphasize and build more like
because they can do things like
self-repair and self-damaging they are
truly adaptive in the sense that I don't
think the robotics that we have today
can do right so things are very brittle
it's very hard you want to I I tell some
of my colleagues you want to sober up
about the state of AI because you know
there's a lot of wonderful things that
current models and systems can do uh but
there's a lot that they can't do I say
go to a robotics conference and you'll
see instantly how far we are from AGI or
even just really powerful AI narrow AI
like to get a robot to get you a cup of
coffee although there's some nice recent
advancements in robotics but we still
have a long ways to go I think to get
and those are the types of problems that
I think emphasize where mortal
computation might play an important role
it really gets into into this other
domain of Robotics that I've been
fascinated with which is neuro Robotics
and neur Robotics says very shortly I
try to distill it is um we want to build
an intelligence system like a like a
brain If you will something that's
biological within the robot it must
learn and do inference and engage with
this environment inside the body of the
robot there is no simulation uh you must
have physical Hardware to do this
otherwise it's not neur robotics
research you're just doing simulated
stuff as I have done
um and so I think mortal computation uh
sort of emphasizes and celebrates those
domains that really require this
entanglement right we want our neural
adaptive systems to actually work in
noisy uncertain environments and the
tools that we have today with back
propagation of errors and reinforcement
learning and modern-day deep neural Nets
they're not always the best they're not
best suited sometimes to these
particular problems so I think that
that's me waxing about the general
problem uh I will comment that while
Transformers and the models that we have
today are doing some really wonderful
things and there's no dismissing of that
uh I do not believe that the the uh key
to artificial general intelligence lies
in that they are very still tool
oriented and while that's important in
stands to make wonderful impacts and
health care and other aspects of
humanity that's not going to get us to
the dreams of original AI right to build
cognitively viable functional General
intelligent systems that can act even
like I'd say even at the level of a
simple animal forget about humanoid
intelligence so I do think moral
computation says maybe we should
consider these Concepts and here's we
even give a definition in the paper it's
not perhaps the most perfect definition
and it'll probably change if more people
work on this um but it gives you some
ideas about how origins of Life tie into
mind and how maybe what are the design
con what are the design principles we
should be considering to actually build
this because another under the hood of
my lab coat if you will is I'm an
engineer so uh and uh someone that I
should mention did some light reviewing
and nice feedback for me not light
reviewing reviewing was my Father which
you might see in the acknowledgements
Alexander Ria senior so just it's not me
thaning myself it's me thinking my dad
um and he had told me in one of the very
earliest drafts of this he says you
should probably emphasize how do you
build this I mean obviously we don't
give you the final answer but that's
where the engineer ing takes are in
there where I try to explain well okay
this is where the sensory motor
dependencies might exist on metabolism
homeostasis allostasis and you notice
that so that's where to encourage the
audience read the paper because we talk
about where autop pieces fits in this
framework and PES so I think that's kind
of one General answer about AGI and I
don't think the current path we have
will get us there uh I could be wrong
Carl and I could be wrong uh now to
address versus and uh versus Ai and
active inference I do believe active
inference is very promising uh again it
might not be the complete story it might
not be all that we need um and I do
think that it is but it is important
that we make advancements in active
inference I think that uh you were you
said very early in this interview that
you discussion that you were talking
about you were gonna mention
reinforcement learning right so may I
can help bring that little tiny sprinkle
in here and say that um I think it's
important that active INF seems to get a
little overshadowed by reinforcement
learning by if you can design a really
good reward function uh you can you know
build a sufficiently operating system
and we're good enough uh but they're
very brittle they don't work very well
in the continual learning setting they
kind of dropic forget it's very hard to
train them online they're sample
inefficient I could go on and on about
all the problems with RL and I think
active inference STS to say wait a
minute maybe we should turn this problem
on its head and you know as long as we
have some definition of a prior
preference which I think is one of the
more difficult components of active
inference to get right but that's the uh
inductive bias that Evolution would give
us so at least it's got the connection
to uh biology uh active inference really
emphasizes that intelligent exploration
and there's some nice results that I've
seen out there that you know reduce the
number of samples that you need to learn
a good policy so I think active
inference represents a really nice
alternative uh to reinforcement learning
and it even has some really nice bio
neurobiological and Cognitive Connection
so it's gives you that like process
Theory it's often called a
neurobiological process theory for
adaptation so I do think that's
important and I'm happy that uh versus
AI uh is uh pushing along that path and
uh obviously I might be a little biased
because I work with Carl I work with
Tomaso salvator he's also there and
Chris Buckley uh so even though I'm not
part of versus Ai and I don't speak for
them in any capacity um obviously I'm
going to be biased because I collaborate
with a lot of the people that are there
um so yeah I thought that was very
diplomatic
uh watching there's no no saying who's
wrong or right I but I do urge I do want
to say I urge everyone to consider
mortal computation and crabs fleshing
that out further because I think there's
still this is a stepping stone paper I
do not by any means think we said oh
just do what we say it's like to get you
thinking right yeah yeah yeah well
hopefully you know in addition to the
paper this has got a lot of people
thinking um but it's got me thinking I'm
gonna and I'm going to go and practice
the pronunciation of homei homeorhesis
homeorhesis and apparently also
Laboratory um I didn't know that one was
a problem um Alex thank you so much um
it's been an absolute Joy um just for
people wanting to know more about you
what you know what work have you got
coming up and if people have got
questions can they reach out to you how
should they reach out to you please uh
uh well first of all I want to thank you
for having me this was discussion I very
much enjoyed talking with you about
Mortal computation and AGI uh and even
poking at the holes in my knowledge
there was a few points there I was like
oh no I'm not a physicist and I should
be clear here
by the way so this was wonderful um in
terms of uh how to reach me I mean
there's uh my email contact I'm also on
LinkedIn apparently that's becoming sort
of more the social science platform I've
noticed as opposed to Twitter X as they
call it nowadays um so uh you can look
me up there and I do now start to engage
with information that people are posting
there and I make announ I just made my
first announcement uh on there about one
work that I would like to highlight here
so while uh Carl and I did this
wonderful uh survey on Mortal
computation and you know kind of
provided definition another massive
survey of mine so if you thought this
was long I have a longer one uh came out
at the end of December it's a a called a
brain inspired machine intelligence a
survey of neurobiological credit
assignment where I also review over the
last several decades as much as I
possibly could I know for a fact I
probably still missed something uh all
the different approaches that have been
uh neurobiologically inspired to
training neural networks or constructing
new neural models that are more
biologically faithful and just don't do
it with back propop so basically
everything that's wrong with backrop and
we look at everything ranging from like
boltzman machines to rec circulant
autoencoders all the way up to Modern
Day stuff including uh Jeff's work on
Ford forward only learning and some
other flavors of signal propagation nice
things so I I really really urge that
one I like to pull uh plug that work
because I also think it's a nice
resource for uh PhD students and posts
who want to maybe engage in uh uh
alternatives to the modern days we do Ai
and I think that gives you a lot of uh
uh uh historical context and it makes
you pay proper credit assignment to the
wonderful Minds so many researchers over
the decades you know sometimes get
overlooked in this uh you know rapidly
mov Information Age so that's one paper
there is one more survey that I also Rec
so last year was the year of surveys for
me another survey on predictive coding I
know you and I didn't really touch a
whole lot on it but um Thomas o
Salvatore is my friend and he and I uh
sort of and Anor mly we set up this
wonderful survey Carl's on there Rish
Ral one one of the most important
figures in predictive Cod Chris
Buckley's on there Thomas LTZ um I
recommend people look up it's like brain
inspired computational intelligence via
predictive coding uh and that reviews
everything that's happened in predictive
coding as much as we could over the last
several years for machine intelligence
so I think I'd like to those two
specific ones they're very Ed and well
we'll put them in the we'll put them in
the video description so people will
have direct access to it as well as the
Mortal computation paper we've been
discussing today perfect and you can
reach me by my email I should last point
I I don't know if you want to give that
in the link to the video or feel free to
say now so that you know um sure ago cs.
rit.edu you can reach me there cool I'm
sure that's on the internet as well um
everything's on the internet Alex thank
you again so much um it's been really
really fun and super informative so
thank you for me from the Institute as
well